A Guide to the Papers of Edwin A. Alderman
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series III: Speeches, Addresses, Articles by Alderman
  - 1921 May Statement concerning the Medical School printed in the Supplement to University of Virginia Alumni News (Box-folder 23:18)
  - 1921 June 1 Welcome Address to the Centennial Celebration at the University of Virginia, typescript (Box-folder 23:19)
  - 1921 June 2 Introductions of Professor John Bassett Moore and British Ambassador Sir Auckland Geddes at the Centennial Celebration at the University of Virginia, typescript (Box-folder 23:20)
  - 1921 June 3 Speech accepting the Centennial Gift of the Alumni Fund (Box-folder 23:21)
  - 1921 June 3 Centennial Address to the Graduates of the University of Virginia Class of 1921, delivered in the Amphitheater, typescript and printed in The Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 23:22)
  - 1921 June 18 & 29 Article "The Centenary of the University of Virginia" in The Outlook, typescript and printed (Box-folder 23:23)
  - [1921 June 23?] Article "The University of Virginia and Medical Education, printed pamphlet" (Box-folder 23:24)
  - 1921 Sep 29 Convocation Address delivered in the Amphitheater, typescript (Box-folder 23:25)
  - 1921 October 14 Welcome Address to the Shriners of Virginia at the University of Virginia, typescript (Box-folder 23:26)
  - 1921 October 19 Speech at the Unveiling of the Statue of Stonewall Jackson by Charles Keck, given by Paul Goodloe McIntire to the City of Charlottesville, typescript (Box-folder 23:27)
  - 1921 October Speech concerning the Alumni Goal for the Centennial Gift, typescripts (Box-folder 23:28)
  - 1921 Nov 3 Acceptance Speech at the Unveiling of the George Rogers Clark Statue by Robert Aitken, given by Paul Goodloe McIntire to the University of Virginia, typescript and printed in The Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 23:29)
  - 1921 Nov 11 Remarks on Armistice Day, typescript (Box-folder 23:30)
  - 1921 Nov 16 Article "The Meaning of Universities" published in World's Work Council Table, Volume 43, pages 248-251, letter and typescript (Box-folder 23:31)
  - 1921 November 22-23 Speech before the [Teacher's Association] Education Meeting, Richmond, Virginia, typescript and printed (Box-folder 23:32)
  - 1921 November Christmas Message to Alumni, printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 23:33)
  - 1921 Centennial Dedication in The Corks and Curls, typescript (Box-folder 23:34)
  - 1922 Jan 26 "The Address of the President of the University before the Joint Committee on Schools and Colleges of the General Assembly of Virginia" printed pamphlet and printed in Alumni Bulletin and a pamphlet (Box-folder 23:35)
  - 1922 April 13 Founder's Day Address spoken in Cabell Hall, typescript and printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 23:36)
  - 1922 May 29 Address at the Semi-Centennial Exercises of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute, typescript (Box-folder 23:37)
  - 1922 June 13 Finals Address to the Graduating Class of 1922, typescript, with a letter from the secretary of Arthur Morris requesting a copy of the speech, December 31, 1925 (Box-folder 23:38)
  - 1922 October 16 Convocation Address, typescript (Box-folder 23:39)
  - 1922 November 8 Book Review "A Great Ambassador A Personal Impression" by Alderman for "The Book Table" in The Outlook for The Life and Letters of Walter H. Page by Burton Hendrick (Box-folder 23:40)
  - 1922 December Christmas Message to Alumni, typescript and printed in Alumni News (Box-folder 23:41)
  - 1922 December Address delivered before the Virginia Horticultural Society Convention at Charlottesville, typescript, with two letters, December 26, 1922 and January 4, 1923, about the speech (Box-folder 23:42)
  - 1923 January Article "A Personal Remembrance" concerning Thomas Nelson Page, typescript, but also printed in Alumni Bulletin, January 1923 (Box-folder 24:1)
  - 1923 February 9 Speech at the United States Naval Academy, typescripts (Box-folder 24:2)
  - 1923 June 12 Commencement Address, printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 24:3)
  - 1923 June Article "A Madison Letter and Some Digressions" typescript and printed, a reprint from the Alumni Bulletin; it was originally published in The North American Review (Box-folder 24:4)
  - 1923 Sep 27 Convocation Address, typescript (Box-folder 24:5)
  - 1923 Dec 3 Address "James Monroe" delivered at Monroe Doctrine Centenary, Richmond, Virginia, typescript and printed in Alumni Bulletin July-August 1924 (Box-folder 24:6)
  - 1923 Dec 5 Paper "Virginia and Higher Education" read before the Institutions of Higher Education, typescript and printed in Alumni Bulletin April 1924 (Box-folder 24:7)
  - 1923 Dec 25 Christmas Message to the Alumni, typescript and printed in Alumni Bulletin December 1923 (Box-folder 24:8)
  - 1924 Jan-Feb Tribute to Charles William Eliot for Review of Reviews, typescript, including correspondence with Albert Shaw, editor, asking Alderman for a contribution to his magazine about Eliot for his 90 th birthday (Box-folder 24:9)
  - 1924 Feb 2 Tribute to Woodrow Wilson in the Richmond News Leader, typescript and correspondence with Douglas Southall Freeman about his tribute (Box-folder 24:10)
  - 1924 Feb 4 Tribute to Woodrow Wilson for The Outlook, typescript and correspondence with the editor, Ernest H. Abbott (Box-folder 24:11)
  - 1924 Feb [11] Article "The University of Virginia: A Record of Growth" written for The Progress-Index of Petersburg, Virginia, typescript and a letter from Walter Edward Harris (Box-folder 24:12)
  - 1924 Feb 14 Speech in Support of Higher Education in Virginia delivered before the Joint Meeting of the Committees of the General Assembly of Virginia concerning a bond issue, etc., typescripts (Box-folder 24:13)
  - 1924 Mar 13 Speech at the Unveiling of the Monument to Governor Brantley Aycock, typescript, paste-up and print version for The Journal of Social Forces, printed in the Raleigh, North Carolina The News and Observer, including correspondence about the speech (Box-folder 24:14)
  - 1924 Apr 7 Speech delivered at the Dinner to the Board of Governors of the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, Hotel Commodore, New York City, typescripts, printed program, and correspondence about his address (Box-folder 24:15)
  - 1924 April 12 Founder's Day Address, Cabell Hall, typescript and printed in Alumni Bulletin, July 1924; including the Founder's Day Address by John Holladay Latane "Jefferson's Influence on American Foreign Policy" (Box-folder 24:16)
  - 1924 May 13 Speech delivered at Unveiling of Jefferson Bust, Hall of Fame, New York University, typescript, printed in Alumni Bulletin, July 1924, printed program, photograph of the Jefferson bust signed by the sculptor, and correspondence about the address (Box-folder 24:17)
  - 1924 May 20 Speech delivered at the Warrenton, Virginia, Library, typescript and correspondence about the speech (Box-folder 24:18)
  - 1924 May 21 Speech delivered at the Unveiling of the Statue of Robert E. Lee conceived by Henry Shrady and executed by Leo Lentelli in Lee Park, Charlottesville, Virginia, typescript, printed in Alumni Bulletin, October 1924, and a letter from Jessica Smith about the flag used during the unveiling of the statue given by Paul Goodloe McIntire (Box-folder 24:19)
  - 1924 June 10 Finals Day Speech delivered in Cabell Hall, University of Virginia, on Democracy, typescript and printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 24:20)
  - 1924 October 2 Convocation Speech, delivered in Cabell Hall, University of Virginia, typescript and printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 24:21)
  - 1924 November 27 Speech for Football Mass Meeting at the Virginia Carolina Game, manuscript (Box-folder 24:22)
  - 1924 Dec 1 House Concurrent Resolution 30 concerning the Memorial Exercises for Woodrow Wilson, printed with letter, December 4, 1924, from Leroy S. Boyd with advice to Alderman about his address (Box-folder 24:23)
  - 1924 Dec 15 Woodrow Wilson Memorial Address delivered before Congress, typescript copy (Box-folder 24:24)
  - 1924 Dec 15 Woodrow Wilson Memorial Address delivered before Congress, copy used in speaking, typescripts, one with a note that brackets indicate he will leave out in speaking to save time but will include in the printed version (Box-folder 24:25)
  - 1924 Dec 15 Woodrow Wilson Memorial Address delivered before Congress, Advance Galley Proofs, Corrected Copy (Box-folder 25:1)
  - 1924 Dec 15 Woodrow Wilson Memorial Address delivered before Congress, card admitting the Bearer [Alderman] to the Floor of the House of Representatives and printed versions of the speech, including Senate Document No. 174; a copy printed in University of Virginia Alumni News, January 1925; Congressional Record Volume 66, No. 13; and a later printed version published by the Modern Eloquence Corporation, 1926 (Box-folder 25:2)
  - 1924-1925 Woodrow Wilson Memorial Address - Materials collected by Alderman about Wilson and Lists of Persons requesting tickets to the event and copies of the speech (Box-folder 25:3)
  - 1924 December 25 Christmas Message to Alumni, typescript and printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 25:3a)
  - 1924-1925 Editorials for the Cosmos Newspaper Syndicate, typescripts, including "The Growth of the South"; "The Statute of Virginia for Religious Freedom"; "Our Debt to George Washington"; "What is Democracy"; "Our Debt to Thomas Jefferson" (Box-folder 25:4)
  - 1925 Jan 24 Speech to the Service Citizens Association of Delaware delivered at DuPont dinner, Wilmington, Delaware, typescript (Box-folder 25:5)
  - 1925 April 8 Article sent to [George Willis] Guy to be used in the May Campaign for Higher Education, typescript (Box-folder 25:6)
  - 1925 April 12 Article "The Nation Exalts Jefferson" published in The New York Times, typescripts and copy of the article (Box-folder 25:7)
  - 1925 April 13 Founder's Day Speech and Introduction of Robert B. Tunstall, typescripts and printed in The Alumni News Bulletin Supplement, April 1925 (Box-folder 25:8)
  - 1925 April 27 Speech concerning Whiskey and Law Enforcement, manuscript (Box-folder 25:9)
  - [1925 April] Paper on "Edgar Allan Poe and the University of Virginia" for the 1 st number of the Virginia Quarterly Review, incomplete typescript (Box-folder 25:10)
  - 1925 June 1 Speech at Goucher College, Baltimore, Maryland, typescript (incomplete) (Box-folder 25:11)
  - 1925 Jun 16 Finals Day Speech to Graduates, typescript, clipping, and printed in The Alumni News Bulletin Supplement, July 1925 (Box-folder 25:12)
  - 1925 October 8 Convocation Address, typescripts (Box-folder 25:13)
  - 1925 October 12 Address delivered at the Semi-Centennial Celebration of the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, typescripts (Box-folder 25:14)
  - 1925 November 25 Address "The Present State of Higher Education in Virginia" delivered before the Virginia Educational Conference at Norfolk, Virginia, typescripts, printed in The Alumni News, December 1925, The Virginia Teacher, January 1926, as a pamphlet by the Central Committee Institutions of Higher Education in Virginia, with some correspondence about its publication (Box-folder 25:15)
  - 1925 December 7 Statement by Alderman for a news release concerning the Medical School Addition, manuscript (Box-folder 25:16)
  - 1925 December 25 Christmas Greeting to Alumni, typescript and printed in The Alumni News, December 1925 (Box-folder 25:17)
  - [1926 March 19-20?] Address delivered to the Association of Social Science and Social Research Workers in the South, typescript (Box-folder 25:18)
  - 1926 April 13 Founder's Day Address, typescript and printed in The Alumni News Bulletin Supplement, April 1926 (Box-folder 25:19)
  - 1926 April 13 Remarks delivered at the laying of the cornerstone of St. Paul's Memorial Church, typescript (Box-folder 25:20)
  - 1926 May 26 Commencement Address delivered at the Waldorf-Astoria to the Graduates of Miss Spence's School for Girls, New York City, various drafts, correspondence, and a clipping of Alderman's letter to the Richmond Times Dispatch responding to some controversy about his remarks (Box-folder 25:21)
  - 1926 June 15 Finals Address "Magnanimitas" typescript and printed pamphlet (Box-folder 25:22)
  - 1926 June 28 [Commencement] Speech delivered at the Hill School, Pottstown, Pennsylvania, typescripts (Box-folder 26:1)
  - 1926 July 4 Speech delivered upon the awarding of the Jefferson Medal to Claude G. Bowers (1879-1958) and Speech introducing the Reverend Dr. Joseph Fort Newton who spoke at the Memorial Meeting at the University of Virginia Amphitheatre, typescripts (Box-folder 26:2)
  - 1926 October 15 Convocation Address, typescripts and printed in The Alumni News, December 1926 (Box-folder 26:3)
  - 1926 November 12 Speech "What Constitutes an Educated Man or Woman" delivered [?] in Bronxville, New York, manuscript and typescripts; also a typed statement replying to criticisms of his speech [also given at Spence School, New York?] by D. Sam Cox and Hugh White in the newspapers (Box-folder 26:4)
  - 1926 [November 24] Notes for a Speech for a Mass Meeting Day before the University of North Carolina-Virginia Football Game, manuscript (Box-folder 26:5)
  - 1926 November 27 Speech "Virginia" delivered at the dedication of the Phi Beta Kappa Memorial at the College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia, and the observance of the Sesquicentennial Anniversary of Phi Beta Kappa, typescripts, printed in The Phi Beta Kappa Key, January 1927, pages 369-374 (Box-folder 26:6)
  - 1926 December 7 Address to the Fruit Growers, manuscript (Box-folder 26:7)
  - 1926 December 7 Christmas Greeting to the Alumni, typescript (Box-folder 26:8)
  - 1927 January 12 Speech "The New Europe and the New Germany" delivered at University Hour, typescripts (Box-folder 26:9)
  - 1927 March 2 Tribute to Sarah Goins, "A Loyal Servant," news clipping from The Daily Progress (Box-folder 26:10)
  - 1927 April 13 Founder's Day Address, typescript and printed from The Alumni News Bulletin Supplement (Box-folder 26:11)
  - 1927 April "A Human Episode with a Foreword" published in The Virginia Quarterly Review, typescript (Box-folder 26:12)
  - 1927 June 14 Finals Speech "Freedom of the Mind," typescript and printed from The Alumni News Bulletin, program and news clipping, and published as a separate pamphlet (Box-folder 26:13)
  - 1927 December 9 Article "An Expression of Dr. Alderman's Views on Italian Culture" sent to Dr. Richard Henry Wilson (1870-1948) (Box-folder 26:14)
  - 1927 December 15 "The President's Page" typescript; printed in The Alumni News (Box-folder 26:15)
  - 1927 December 19 "Introduction" for Jefferson and Monticello by Paul Wilstach, manuscript and typescript (Box-folder 26:16)
  - 1927 December 25 Christmas Message to the Alumni, typescript (Box-folder 26:17)
  - [1927] Notes and Drafts of Speeches concerning the League of Nations and Europe, manuscript and printed pamphlet "The Front Door to the League of Nations An Address" by Manley O. Hudson (Box-folder 26:18)
  - 1928 January "The President's Page" typescript; printed in The Alumni News (Box-folder 26:19)
  - 1928 March 4 Speech for 50 th Anniversary Celebration of the Pastorate of Dr. George Laurens Petrie (1840-1931) in the Charlottesville Presbyterian Church, typescript and printed in Presbyterian of the South (Box-folder 26:20)
  - 1928 March 7 Report Submitted by the Chairman [Alderman], Subcommittee on Education Second Meeting of the Advisory Council of the National Broadcasting Company, typescript and printed (Box-folder 26:21)
  - 1928 April 19 Speech "Alpha Omega Alpha," typescript (Box-folder 26:22)
  - 1928 June 11-12 Finals Speeches to Graduates and Alumni, typescripts (Box-folder 26:23)
  - 1928 June 19 Greetings to Summer School, typescript (Box-folder 26:24)
  - 1928 October 2 Speech "The Strength of Democracy" delivered before the American Bankers Association Convention, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, typescripts and printed in The Tarheel Banker, November 1928, Volume VII, No. 5 (Box-folder 26:25)
  - 1928 October Convocation Speech, typescript (Box-folder 26:26)
  - [1928] Nov 13 Speech for the [International] Goodwill Congress and 13th annual meeting, American Council, New York, New York, November 11-13, undelivered by Alderman, typescripts (Box-folder 26:27)
  - 1928 November Article "Defining an Alumnus and His Duties to His Alma Mater" sent to Cornell Alumni Association, typescript (Box-folder 26:28)
  - 1928 December 5 "A Letter from President Edwin Anderson Alderman to Governor Harry Flood Byrd," concerning prohibition and the charges of drinking at the University of Virginia, printed in The Alumni News and as a separate pamphlet (Box-folder 26:29)
  - 1928 December 25 Christmas Message to the Alumni, typescript (Box-folder 26:30)
  - 1928 December 28 Letter to Richmond Times Dispatch concerning what Alderman wanted the year 1929 to bring to the Commonwealth of Virginia (Box-folder 26:31)
  - 1928 Notes for a campaign speech on Alfred E. Smith, manuscript (Box-folder 27:1)
  - 1929 January Speech to the Richmond Alumni - Notes and typescript (Box-folder 27:2)
  - 1929 March 4 Statement sent to RCA concerning the radio, typescript (Box-folder 27:3)
  - 1929 April 13 Founder's Day Address and Introduction of the Honorable Vincent Massey, Canadian Minister to the United States, typescript and printed in The Alumni News (Box-folder 27:4)
  - [1929 April 13?] Introduction of Guest Speaker Dr. George Edgar Vincent (date is written on manuscript but Vincent was not the Founder's Day speaker for 1929) (Box-folder 27:5)
  - 1929 April 17 Speech to New York Alumni, New York City, manuscript and typescript (Box-folder 27:6)
  - 1929 May 24 Memorandum on the Needs of the University of Virginia in response to a request from Douglas Southall Freeman to use in his article "Appraisal of Virginia," typescript (Box-folder 27:7)
  - 1929 May 28 Commencement Speech at the Medical College of Virginia, typescript (Box-folder 27:8)
  - 1929 June 10 Speech at the Alumni Luncheon accepting the Alumni gift, typescript and printed in The Alumni News (Box-folder 27:9)
  - 1929 June 10-11 Finals Speeches to Graduates and Alumni and Introduction of Governor Harry F. Byrd, typescripts and clipping about the celebration of Alderman's 25 th Anniversary at the University of Virginia (Box-folder 27:10)
  - 1929 June 21 Speech "Science and Research in the Service of Business" delivered at the Virginia Bankers Association Meeting, Old Point Comfort, Virginia, typescripts and printed in the University of Virginia Record Extension Series (Box-folder 27:11)
  - 1929 August Article "What Mean You by Excellence" in Alumni Bulletin of the University of North Carolina, possibly by Alderman, whose picture is on the first page with the article, printed (Box-folder 27:12)
  - 1929 October 7 Welcome Speech to the Women's Christian Temperance Union, typescripts (Box-folder 27:13)
  - 1929 October 13 Greetings from Alderman regretting his absence at homecoming time in North Carolina, printed in The News and Observer, Raleigh, North Carolina (Box-folder 27:14)
  - 1929 October 22 Speech for the Dedication of the Medical Building, typescript, news clipping, and printed in The Alumni News (Box-folder 27:15)
  - 1929 October Convocation Speech, typescripts (Box-folder 27:16)
  - 1929 November 20 Speech at the Dedication of Salle Lafayette [French Room in the Romance Pavilion] and its acceptance by the University of Virginia, typescripts, news clippings, and printed in The Alumni News and College Topics (Box-folder 27:17)
  - 1930 January Report Submitted by the Chairman [Alderman], Subcommittee on Education Meeting of the Advisory Council of the National Broadcasting Company, typescript (Box-folder 27:18)
  - 1930 February 4 Notes for the Speech concerning a Liberal Arts College for Women delivered before the [General Assembly?], Richmond, Virginia, manuscript (Box-folder 27:19)
  - 1930 February 28 Statement concerning Adult Education, typescript (Box-folder 27:20)
  - 1930 April 13 Founder's Day Address, typescript (Box-folder 27:21)
  - 1930 April 14 Radio Speech - Tribute to Thomas Jefferson, typescripts, press release, and news clippings (Box-folder 27:22)
  - 1930 May 26 Speech "Relations Between the Church and State Institutions of Higher Training" delivered before the General Assembly of the Presbyterian Church in the United States in Session at Charlottesville, Virginia, typescripts, printed pamphlet and printed in The Christian Observer, news clippings (Box-folder 28:1)
  - 1930 May 26 Speech "Relations Between the Church and State Institutions of Higher Training" - Material Used in Preparation of the Speech (Box-folder 28:2)
  - 1930 June 9-10 Finals Speeches to Graduates and Alumni and Introduction of Murray Mason McGuire, typescripts (Box-folder 28:3)
  - 1930 August 3 Address of Welcome to the Fourth Institute of Public Affairs, typescripts (Box-folder 28:4)
  - 1930 August 11 Acceptance Speech for the Portrait of Charles Gilmore Maphis (1865-1925), painted by Seymour Millais Stone (1877- ), and given by Chester DeWitt Pugsley (1887- ), typescript (Box-folder 28:5)
  - 1930 October 5 Convocation Address, typescript (Box-folder 28:6)
  - 1930 October [25] Greetings to Washington and Lee University upon the Inauguration of Francis Pendleton Gaines, typescript (Box-folder 28:7)
  - 1930 October 30 Speech before the Optical Society of America, typescript (Box-folder 28:8)
  - 1930 December 7 Acceptance Speech for the Commemorative Tablet honoring William Barton Rogers, typescript (Box-folder 28:9)
  - 1930 December 29 Welcome Speech to the American Philosophical Association Eastern Division, typescript (Box-folder 28:10)
  - [1930] Greetings to Francis Pendleton Gaines as President of Washington and Lee University, typescript (Box-folder 28:11)
  - [ca. 1930] Greetings to Randolph-Macon College upon its Centennial Celebration, typescript (Box-folder 28:12)
  - [ca. 1930] Speech to a Farmer's Congress, manuscript (Box-folder 28:13)
  - [1930?] Greeting to three Governors - Trinkle, Byrd, and Pollard, meeting [about education?], typescript (Box-folder 28:14)
  - 1931 January 3 Speech introducing Lord and Lady Astor, manuscript and typescript (Box-folder 28:15)
  - 1931 January 8 Speech "Ideals and Objectives of the University of Virginia" delivered during College Hour, typescripts and news clippings (Box-folder 28:16)
  - 1931 January Report of the Chairman [Alderman], Committee on Education, [Meeting of the Advisory Council of the National Broadcasting Company?], typescript (Box-folder 28:17)
  - 1931 March 5 Statement for College Topics concerning changes since the World War (Box-folder 28:18)
  - 1931 March Statement on the Benefits of Prohibition printed in The Southern Collegian and a news clipping (Box-folder 28:19)
  - [1931 April 11-14] Welcoming Address to the first statewide Music Festival held in the Commonwealth, typescript (Box-folder 28:20)
  - 1931 April 13 Founder's Day Address, manuscript and typescript (Box-folder 28:21)
  - 1931 April 13 Speech introducing the Honorable Michael MacWhite (Box-folder 28:22)
  - 1931 April Speech to have been delivered on May 1, 1931 at the Installation of Harry Woodburn Chase as President of the University of Illinois; Alderman died on the train en route to Illinois; typescripts and printed in The University of Virginia Club Bulletin, of New York City (Box-folder 28:23)
  - n.y. December University Hour Lecture, typescript (Box-folder 28:24)
  - n.d. Welcoming Address to the Presbyterian Synod of Virginia, West Virginia, Maryland and the District of Columbia, concerning the practice of religion at the University of Virginia and Thomas Jefferson, typescript (Box-folder 28:25)
  - n.d. Speech delivered to the Bankers of New York, typescript (Box-folder 28:26)